so we finished talking about the basic
examples of spinners in physics starting
with this video we're going to start
looking at Spinners from a purely
mathematical point of view in both 3D
space and 4D space time
in this video we're going to see how we
can rewrite a 3D Vector as a 2x2 matrix
called a poly vector and in the next
video we're going to see how we can
Factor this polyvector into a pair of
poly spinners
later we'll see how we can do the same
thing for a 4D space-time vector and
Factor it into a pair of vial spinners
for the next few videos we're going to
be starting over and inventing Spinners
from scratch so you won't actually
require any of the previous videos to
understand what's going on however the
previous videos might help give more
context for why we care about spinners
I've included a list of sources for this
video in the description if you want to
learn more
so writing a vector as a two by two
Matrix like this probably looks pretty
random but it turns out that this 2x2
matrix is very useful for when we want
to do geometric Transformations on our
Vector like Reflections and rotations
in order to understand why this form is
useful we need to spend a bit of time
talking about the poly matrices also
called the sigma matrices
later in this video we'll see how these
matrices can help us reflect and rotate
vectors
so here are the three poly matrices
Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z
these are also called Sigma 1 Sigma 2
and sigma 3 in some sources
these matrices have some nice properties
that make them useful for doing geometry
first they have zero Trace second
they're all hermitian third they all
square to the identity Matrix fourth we
can always swap the order of two Sigma
matrices in a product if we include a
negative sign
another way of saying this is saying
that the sigma matrices anti-commute
let's review each of these properties in
order
the trace of a matrix is just the sum of
the elements along the main diagonal
it's pretty easy to see that each Sigma
Matrix has zero Trace
let's move on to the hermitian property
remember the transpose of a matrix
denoted with t just means we flip a
matrix's rows and columns but when
matrices have complex entries we're
usually more interested in the hermitian
conjugate denoted with a dagger symbol
this means that we take the transpose of
the Matrix and take the complex
conjugate of each entry
which flips the sign of each imaginary
eye
all three sigma matrices are hermitian
which means they are equal to their own
hermitian conjugates
both Sigma X and sigma Z are real
matrices so we can just take the
transpose to see this and ignore the
complex conjugate
for Sigma y we first flip the rows and
columns which exchanges plus I and minus
I then the complex conjugate flips the
plus and minus signs so we end up back
where we started
so all Sigma matrices are equal to their
own daggers
the third property says that all Sigma
matrices Square to the identity Matrix
which I'm going to denote with this
fancy number one for this video
I'll show this explicitly for Sigma y
the inner product of the first row and
the First Column gives us plus I times
minus I and since I squared equals
negative one this is just negative minus
one or plus one
the other inner products give us 0 0 and
another plus one which is the identity
Matrix
you can check that Sigma X and sigma Z
also Square to the identity Matrix
the final property is that given the
product of two different Sigma matrices
this product equals the negative of the
same two Sigma matrices multiplied in
the opposite order
I'll show this explicitly for Sigma y
times Sigma Z which gives the components
0 I I and zero
if we reverse the product and do Sigma Z
times Sigma y we get the components 0
negative I negative I and zero which is
the negative of the results we got
before
you can check for yourself that this
property also applies to multiplying the
other pairs of Sigma matrices
these last two properties that Sigma
matrices Square to the identity and
anti-commute can be summarized by this
formula the Delta symbol here is called
the chronicer Delta which equals one if
the I and J indices are the same and
equal zero if they are different
basically if we put the same Sigma
Matrix in for both I and J both products
Square to the identity so we get 2 times
the identity
but if the two Sigma matrices are
different then the anti-commutative
property means the terms cancel to zero
this formula can be shortened even
further using this notation where these
curly brackets denotes the
anti-commutator of two matrices
now that we've studied the properties of
the sigma matrices we're going to
introduce the polyvector form of writing
a vector we normally write a 3D vector v
with components x y z as a linear
combination of the basis vectors e x e y
and e z each scaled by the components
what we're going to do now is replace
the basis vectors with the three sigma
matrices so that we now have a linear
combination of the sigma matrices
if we write the matrices explicitly
multiply in the components and add them
together we get this 2 by 2 Matrix
we call this a polyvector and it's an
alternative way of writing a 3D vector
polyvectors are also traceless since the
individual Sigma matrices are traceless
and polyvectors are hermitian since each
of their individual Sigma matrices are
also hermitian
you can also check for yourself that
multiplying a poly matrix by itself will
give the vectors squared length times
the identity Matrix
this polyvector might seem strange but
it's very useful for doing geometric
Transformations such as Reflections and
rotations
remember if we want to reflect our
Vector along the z-axis we just leave
the X and Y components alone and flip
the sign of the Z component this
basically treats the X Y plane as a
mirror and reflects our Vector reversing
the sign along the Z Direction
I'm now going to introduce an operation
called conjugation
when we conjugate by Sigma Z it means we
multiply on the left by Sigma Z and on
the right by Sigma Z inverse
for example conjugating Sigma X by Sigma
Z looks like this
the colors here don't mean anything
they're just to make the formula more
readable
however since Sigma Z squares to the
identity it is its own inverse so we can
just ignore the inverse symbol here
since we know the sigma matrices
anti-commute we can flip the order of
Sigma X and sigma Z here and get a
negative sign
and replace this product of Sigma Z's by
the identity so we get Negative Sigma X
conjugating Sigma y by Sigma Z also
gives us negative Sigma y
conjugating Sigma Z by Sigma Z just
gives us positive Sigma Z since there's
no swapping needed to simplify
so if we want to reflect a vector along
the z-axis we need to flip the sign of
the Z component
but here we've done the exact opposite
of that we've flipped every component
sign except the Z component
but this is easy to fix we just put a
negative sign in front of our
conjugation so negative conjugation by
Sigma Z will flip the sign of the Z
component and leave all the other
components alone
now watch what happens when we take a
general poly vector v and negative
conjugate by Sigma Z
we can expand our polyvector as a linear
combination of the sigma matrices
and pull all the vector components out
in front since they are just numbers
we know all these negative conjugations
leave the X and Y components unchanged
and flips the sign of the Z component
so we've showed that negative
conjugating a polyvector by Sigma Z will
reflect the vector along the z-axis
we can get similar formulas for doing
Reflections along the X and Y axes
it turns out that we can reflect a
vector along any direction that we like
we just pick a unit Vector U of length
one pointing in the direction of the
reflection and negative conjugate our
poly vector v
remember Since U is a polyvector of
length one and squaring a polyvector
gives its squared length times the
identity Matrix U squared should just
equal the identity Matrix
to see that the reflection actually
happens lets negative conjugate V by a
unit Vector U we can break up V into a
portion that's parallel with u and
perpendicular to U
the parallel part would just be U scaled
by some Factor K and for the
perpendicular vectors it turns out we
can swap their order if we pick up a
negative sign
we can collapse these products to
identities and rewrite U times K as the
parallel portion of V
so we see that the portion of V that's
parallel to U has been reversed well the
perpendicular part has been left
unchanged this is exactly what we want
for reflections
to prove this anti-commuting property
that we used for perpendicular vectors
you can pause the video and look at
these slides
the sigma matrices are also useful for
doing rotations of vectors
the key to doing a rotation is
understanding that a rotation can be
viewed as a pair of reflections
let's say that we have this flag and
reflect it in this mirror so that the
flag is pointing in the opposite
direction
now let's reflect it again in this
mirror
the result is just a rotated version of
our original flag so this shows us that
a rotation is basically just like two
reflections
also notice that the angle of the flag's
rotation is equal to twice the angle
between the two mirrors that we used so
if the angle of rotation is Theta then
the angle between the mirrors is Theta
over two
let's try reflecting our poly Vector
once along the x-axis and once along the
y-axis to see what we get
geometrically reflecting along X and
then along y looks like this it's a 180
degree rotation in the X Y plane
this makes sense since the angle between
our mirrors is 90 degrees and the
resulting rotation is twice that 180
degrees
let's try doing this algebraically
to reflect along X we do a negative
sandwich with Sigma X
to reflect along y we do a negative
sandwich with Sigma y
the negative signs cancel since we know
the sigma matrices are hermitian we can
add daggers to them without changing
anything
we also know from linear algebra that we
can replace a product of daggered
matrices if we reverse their order and
Dagger the entire product
so basically daggering a pair of sigmas
is the same as reversing their order
so this is the formula for doing a 180
degree rotation in the X Y plane and if
we work through the algebra we find that
the X and Y components get reversed as
expected for a 180 degree rotation
now just for curiosity's sake let's see
what happens if we try transforming V
using a single-sided transformation
instead of a double-sided transformation
if we work through the algebra we get
that the X Y components have been
rotated by 90 degrees in the X Y plane
however the Z component has come out
wrong with sigmas that cannot be
meaningfully simplified
so doing a double-sided transformation
is required to make all the basis sigmas
work out properly
now what if we wanted to rotate our poly
vector by an arbitrary angle Theta we
would need two mirrors separated by an
angle of theta over two
we could start with reflecting along the
x-axis then use another reflection
Vector angled at Theta over 2 compared
to the x-axis
when we do these two Reflections the
negative signs cancel and after
Distributing the sigma X squareds become
identity matrices and we can swap the
order of these sigmas by changing the
sign in front
we can also write the right side term as
the hermitian conjugate of the left side
term since the hermitian conjugate swaps
the order of the sigmas
so this is our formula for rotating in
the X Y plane you'll notice that I'm
using angles of theta over 2 here that's
because each side of the transformation
will rotate by Theta over two giving us
a rotation of theta in total
keep in mind that if the angle between
the mirrors is zero we just reflect in
the same mirror twice leading to no
change as expected
if I try to calculate this rotation the
algebra between all the sigmas gets
pretty tedious it's easier to write
things out as matrices looking at this
left expression and writing out the
matrices we get this and we can rewrite
the cosines and signs as complex
exponentials
the left Matrix multiplies the top row
of our polyvector by a negative
exponential and the bottom row by a
positive exponential
after taking the hermitian conjugate of
the right Matrix we get similar
multiplications for the left column and
right column of our polyvector
the exponentials next to the Z's cancel
and we end up with a complex exponential
multiplying R X and Y components by a
phase of theta
taking this entry and multiplying things
out the real part is our new X component
and the imaginary part is our new y
component
these Transformations match exactly what
we'd get from a rotation Matrix in three
dimensions by an angle Theta in the X Y
plane so our two-sided transformation of
our polyvector worked
we can get similar matrices for
rotations in the YZ plane and ZX plane
it turns out that all of these matrices
are special unitary two by two matrices
or su2 matrices meaning they are all
unitary and have determinants of one
as an exercise you can try proving that
all of these matrices are unitary by
multiplying them by their hermitian
conjugate and getting the identity
Matrix
see if you can do it using only the
properties of the sigma matrices without
writing the matrices explicitly
so poly vectors are rotated by a
double-sided transformation of su2
matrices
let's see if we can prove this fact
definitively
as a starting point we're going to
assume that rotating a polyvector can be
done with a double-sided transformation
with matrices A and B
we're going to use the properties of
poly vectors to deduce What A and B
should look like
we already know that polyvectors are
hermitian and have zero Trace but
another important property of rotating a
3D Vector is that its length will not
change after the rotation
so we expect the squared length x
squared plus y squared plus Z squared to
be unchanged after rotation
notice that when we take the determinant
of our polyvector we get Z times
negative Z minus this times this
and simplifying this becomes negative x
squared minus y squared
so the determinant of our poly Vector is
the negative of the vectors squared
length
so when we rotate our polyvector its
determinant which is the vectors
negative squared length should not
change
using these three properties we can
deduce the form of the A and B matrices
since polyvectors are hermitian the
resulting poly Vector after the
transformation should also be hermitian
and remember the hermitian conjugate of
a product is the product of the
individual hermitian conjugates in the
reverse order
since V equals V dagger we get this
formula
we can use this as a hint to assume that
the B Matrix should equal a dagger so
our transformation looks like a v a
dagger
next we want to know that the
determinant or negative squared length
of our poly Vector should not change
after the transformation so these two
determinants must be equal
if we recall that the determinant of a
product is just the product of the
determinants we can cancel the
determinant of v on both sides
the transpose does not change the
determinant results so we ignore it and
we can bring the complex conjugate
outside
so we end up with the squared magnitude
of the determinant of a being 1.
this means that the determinant of a can
be any complex number with magnitude one
meaning it's a complex number on the
unit circle of the form e to the I Theta
however there's an important detail we
need to pay attention to with
double-sided transformations
let's try replacing our Matrix a with a
times a complex phase
the phase on the right will get complex
conjugated because of the hermitian
conjugate causing it to cancel with the
phase on the left
the resulting transformation is the
exact same as the one before we
multiplied by the phase
this means that there are multiple a
matrices that lead to the same
transformation all related by different
phase factors
so there is a redundancy in the a
matrices for doing rotations
we can pick out a specific a matrix by
picking the one whose determinant is
equal to one
if a has a determinant of e to the I
Theta we can always Force its
determinant to be one by multiplying by
a phase of e to the negative I Theta
over two
this phase will have no impact on the
transformation due to the phase
cancellation property of double-sided
transformations
so the phase drops out anyway
but we can successfully Force the
determinant of a to be one
so by using the properties of
determinants and eliminating the
redundancies in the phase we can say
that a has a determinant of positive one
finally since poly vectors have zero
trace the result of the transformation
should also have zero Trace
when we have the trace of a product of
matrices a theorem from linear algebra
tells us that we can cycle the product
order bringing the last one and putting
it in front
now since the trace of V is 0 for any
possible V the only way for this Trace
to be zero is if a dagger a equals the
identity Matrix times a constant
this can be shown by checking the
various cases of v and solving for the
Matrix entries of a dagger a
taking the determinant of this formula
we already know from the last step that
the determinant of a is one so k equals
plus or minus one meaning a dagger times
a equals plus or minus the identity
Matrix
however the product a dagger times a is
guaranteed to have positive entries
along the diagonal
so the only option is that a dagger a
equals the identity Matrix in other
words a dagger equals a inverse
the fact that a dagger equals a inverse
means that a is a member of the group of
two by two unitary matrices U2
and the fact that it has a determinant
of one means it's from the group of two
by two special unitary matrices su2
where the word special means the
determinant is one
so what we've shown is in order to
rotate the poly vector by some angle we
do a double-sided Matrix transformation
like this with su2 matrices
this is a direct result of polyvectors
being traceless hermitian and having a
determinant that's equal to the negative
squared length of a vector which must be
unchanged by rotations
now what do su2 matrices actually look
like if we take an su2 Matrix a with
complex entries Alpha Beta Gamma Delta
we know that a dagger involves flipping
the off diagonal components and complex
conjugating all the entries
we also know that the inverse of any
general two by two Matrix will take this
form
since the determinant of an su2 Matrix
is one we can set this to one
and since a dagger equals a inverse we
immediately get that Delta equals the
complex conjugate of Alpha and Gamma
equals the negative complex conjugate of
beta
so all su2 matrices take this form where
the determinant equals one so the
squared magnitude of alpha plus the
squared magnitude of beta equals one
the three rotation matrices we saw
earlier match this form so they are
indeed su2 matrices
also note that su2 matrices have two
complex parameters or four real
parameters
however since the determinant is forced
to be one this gives one extra
constraint reducing the four real
parameters to three real parameters
as there are three independent planes of
rotation that we can choose angles for
another thing to notice is that the
positive version of an su2 Matrix and
the negative version of an su2 Matrix
perform the exact same rotation
since the negative signs cancel out in
the double-sided transformation
this means that for every 3x3 rotation
Matrix in the group SO3 there are two
corresponding rotation matrices in su2
that do the same rotation
we'll see later that this means su2 is
the double cover of SO3
so to summarize this video we saw that
the sigma matrices also called poly
matrices obey these special
anti-commutation relations
and this allows them to easily perform
geometric Transformations on polyvectors
Reflections are performed by doing
negative conjugation on a polyvector and
rotations are performed by doing
double-sided Transformations like this
where these matrices are su2 matrices
each of the two matrices performs half
the rotation so we use half angles
inside the Matrix entries
in the next video we're going to see how
we can factor a poly Vector into a pair
of poly Spinners each poly spinner will
rotate using only a single su2 Matrix
this is why poly spanners rotate half as
much as vectors do and require two full
rotations to get back to their starting
point